再见
Bye-bye.
我在米雪餐厅订好位子了…
I just got reservations at Michelle's...
还有《音乐人》的票来庆祝…
...and tickets to The Music Man to celebrate...
我们成为"顶婚"夫妻后 第一个正式的节日
...our first holiday as a betrothed couple.
- 是"订婚"   - 订婚夫妻
- "Betrothed."     - Betrothed couple.
- 嘿    - 嗨
- Hey.     - Hi.
- 啊   - 哦
- Aw.     - Oh.
- 菲比？ - 哈？
- Pheebs?     - Uh-huh?
骷髅头？
Skull?
是啊 是我妈的
Oh. Yeah, it's my mom's.
我的天
Oh, my God!
不 不 不 不是我妈
No, no, no. It's not my mom.
是属于我妈的
It belonged to my mom.
她以前每次圣诞节都会拿出来…
She used to put it out every Christmas...
要我们记得即使是圣诞节 人还是会死的
...to remind us that even though it's Christmas, people still die.
还可以放糖果在里面
And you can put candy in it.
- 嘿   - 嘿
- Hey.     - Hey.
吃糖？
Licorice?
好啊
Sure. Ha, ha.
- 今年班和我一起过节   - 太好了
- I get Ben for the holidays this year.     - That's great!
- 你要扮成圣诞老公公吗？ - 不要
- Are you gonna dress up as Santa?     - Nope.
我知道苏珊每年都这么做…
I know Susan does every year.
可是今年我想教他了解光明节
I want to take this year to teach him about Hanukkah.
也许我能教班…
And maybe I could teach Ben...
有关圣诞骷髅头和人怎么死亡
...about the Christmas skull and how people die.
你可以在今年教班认识菲比
You may need to use this year to teach Ben about Phoebe.
嗯
Mm.
嘿
Hey.
- 你知道他在里面吗？ - 不知道
- Did you know he was in there?     - No.
- 我们回来多久了？ - 大概半小时
- How long have we been home?     - About half an hour.
好极了
Lovely.
(中央咖啡厅)
你知道我在想什么？ 我们结婚后 你要不要…
You know what I was thinking? When we get married, will you, uh...
改冠夫姓"宾"？
...change your name to "Bing"?
不要
No.
为什么不要？
Why not?
"宾"很奇怪
Bing's weird.
你们好
Oh, hey, you guys.
- 嘿   - 嘿
- Hey.    - Hey
你猜怎么了？
Guess what?
猜猜怎么着 我房东刚刚通知我 我的房子快好了
My landlord just called. My apartment's gonna be ready soon.
所以我很快就会搬出去了
I guess I'll be moving out.
菲比 我会想念你的
Aw, Phoebe, I'm gonna miss you.
是啊 你会很伤心
Yes, you will be very sad.
- 我要告诉瑞秋这个好消息   - 你们要再住在一起吗？
- I gotta go tell Rachel the good news.     - Oh. You'll be living together again?
- 是啊 为什么不？ - 她和乔伊住得很开心…
- Why not?     - She's having so much fun with Joey...
我以为她还会 继续和他住在一起
...I assumed she'd still be living with him.
为什么你认为 她和乔伊住得很开心？
Why do you think she's having so much fun?
没为什么 只不过…
No reason, except she...
她是这么跟我说的
...told me.
真的？她说她不要和我住？
She said she didn't want to live with me?
没有 她没这么说
No. No, she didn't say that.
我想你该和摩妮卡说话了
I think you should talk to Monica now.
菲比 别担心 我确定她想和你住的
Phoebe, I'm sure she wants to live with you.
你确定？你很肯定？
You're absolutely sure?
不 我打赌她大概会
No, but I'll bet she probably does.
大概？
Oh, probably?
我不喜欢这个词
I don't like that word.
我知道"大概"真正的意思 是啊 是啊
I know what "probably" really means. Yeah, uh-huh, yeah.
"你妈大概不会自杀"
"Oh, your mom probably won't kill herself."
对不起 我不要把我和瑞秋…
You know. I'm sorry, but I'm not hanging my hopes...
住在一起的希望寄托在"大概"上面
...of Rachel and I living together on "probably."
人在这世上要自己照顾自己
You gotta take care of yourself in this world.
历史教训完全没用
History teaches us nothing.
"宾"现在不是那么奇怪了吧？
Bing doesn't seem so weird now, does it?
太好了 你在家
You're home.
猜猜菲比送我什么圣诞礼物
Guess what Phoebe got me for Christmas?
- 鼓？ - 不 鼓
- Drums?     - No, drums!
嗨 请给我们两个墨西哥卷外带
Could we get two burritos to go, please? Ha, ha.
抱歉 不过没那么抱歉 因为你不用和他在一起生活
I'm sorry. But not that sorry, you don't have to live with it.
我们用钱德宾的名字订了位子
Um, we have a reservation under Bing.
好的 大约要等45分钟
Okay, we'll have a table for you in about 45 minutes.
45分钟？《音乐人》的票是8点的
We have tickets to The Music Man at 8.
抱歉 圣诞节是最忙的时候
I'm sorry. Christmas is a very busy time, sir.
这是因为墨西哥卷的玩笑吗？
Is this because of the burrito thing?
- 要给他钱   - 给他钱？那只是个玩笑
- You need to give him money.     - Give him money? It was a joke!
不 为了我们的位子 这种地方都是死要钱的
To get a table. Places like this are always shaking you down.
- 每个人都要小费   - 好 镇静下来
- Everybody wants a payoff.     - All right, calm down, O'Malley.
- 我会塞钱给他   - 可是要不着痕迹
- I'll slip him some money.     - But you've got to be smooth.
嘿 我可以不着痕迹
Hey, I can be smooth.
我们有点赶时间 如果可以让我们早一点…
We're in a hurry. If you could get us a table...
排到位子 我会很感激
...a bit quicker, I'd appreciate it.
- 当然 先生   - 好
- Of course, sir.     - Okay.
- 怎么样？ - 钱在另一只手里
- How'd it go?     - Had the money in the wrong hand.
你不觉得的…
You don't feel...
你要扔了吗？ - 没有
...like you're gonna throw up? - No.
我会 所以我们…
Well, I do. So let's...
班 你…
So, Ben, you, uh...
你知道快过节了 对不对？
You know what holiday is coming up?
圣诞节
Christmas.
对 你知道另一个节日也要到了？
Yeah, and you know what other holiday is coming up?
圣诞夜
Christmas Eve.
对 但…
Yes, but also...
光明节也是
Hanukkah!
你是一半犹太人 光明节是犹太人的节日
See, you're part Jewish and Hanukkah is a Jewish holiday.
圣诞老公公有会飞的麋鹿
Santa has reindeers that can fly.
对 但在光明节…
Right, um, but on Hanukkah...
光明节是庆祝一个奇迹
Hanukkah is a celebration of a miracle.
很多年前 有一群人叫做玛加伯人
Years and years ago there were these people called the Maccabees.
叮叮当 叮叮当
Jingle bells, jingle bells
好 对 是的…
Okay, that's right. Yes...
但在光明节 我们唱的是
...but on Hanukkah, we sing, uh:
陀螺 陀螺 陀螺 我给你做粘土
Dreidel, dreidel, dreidel I made you out of clay
鲁道夫 红鼻子的驯鹿
Rudolph the red-nosed reindeer
好 这不是在比赛
Ha, ha. Okay, it's not a contest.
圣诞老公公什么时候来？
When is Santa coming?
这样好不好 今年我们 不要圣诞老公公…
How about this year, instead of Santa...
我们来庆祝光明节？
...we have fun celebrating Hanukkah?
没有圣诞老公公？
No Santa?
我不乖吗？
Was I bad?
不 不 你没有不乖 你今年很乖 班
No, no, no, you weren't bad. You've been very good, Ben.
- 圣诞老公公生我的气   - 不是 嘿 嘿
- Santa's mad at me.     - No, hey, hey, come on.
班 圣诞老公公 没有生你的气 好吗？
Ben, Santa is not mad at you, okay?
你是他最喜欢的小孩
You're his favorite little guy.
所以圣诞老公公会来罗？
So Santa's coming?
对
Yes!
圣诞老公公会来
Santa's coming.
很简单  保持轻松
It's easy. Just keep it casual.
说句好话  和他握手 塞钱给他
Shake his hand and give him the money.
- 你怎么这么了解？ - 我不知道
- How do you know so much about this?     - I don't know.
理查以前常这么做 是不是？
Richard used to do it, didn't he?
我们现在可能已经在喝汤了
We'd be eating our soup right now.
可恶的小胡子
Mustached bastard.
这些人刚走 快 给他钱
Those people just left. Come on. Quick, give him the money.
对不起
Excuse me.
我们赶时间 可不可以…？
We're in a bit of a hurry. Can we please?
啊 哈哈哈
Ah-ha-ha-ha.
哈
Ha!
你喜欢鼓啊
So you like the drums.
真好
That's great.
我本来还担心它们会造成…
I was worried that they would create maybe...
无法忍耐的居住状况
...an unbearable living situation.
好吧 看来没有 好
But, okay, well, apparently not. So, yay!
菲比 我们学会了一首歌
Hey, we already learned a song.
准备好了？1 2 3 4
Ready? One, two, three, four.
塔奇拉
Tequila!
真好玩
That's fun.
来了
Here you go.
谢谢 阿甘 放在这里
Thank you, Gunther. Put her there.
用铜板更不容易
Definitely not easier with coins.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 菲比   - 嘿
- Hey, Pheebs.     - Hey.
给你 现在我只欠你49块半
Here. Now I only owe you $49.50.
- 菲比…   - 嘿
- Hey, Pheebs.     - Hey.
如果你要送乔伊 毁掉整栋楼的圣诞礼物…
If you want to get Joey a gift that disrupts the entire building...
何不送更微妙一点的…
...why not something more subtle...
像是铁锤…
...like a wrecking ball...
或是天花病毒散播在走廊上？
...or a vial of smallpox to release in the hallway?
不只是鼓的声音 每5分钟…
It's not just the drum noise. Every five minutes...
乔伊把鼓棒丢到空中…
...Joey throws his sticks in the air...
然后我就会听到  "喔 我的眼睛 我的眼睛 "
...and I have to hear: "Oh, my eye! Oh, God, my eye!"
- 烦死人了   - 对 谢谢你
- I mean, it's so annoying.     - Yes, thank you.
你看 这是正常人对鼓的反应
You see, this is how normal people are supposed to react to drums.
菲比 你送乔伊鼓是为了烦瑞秋…
You got Joey drums to annoy Rachel...
让她不想继续住在那里？
...so she wouldn't want to live there anymore?
可能有一点
Maybe on some level.
乔伊 你知道你不用丢鼓棒的
You could just not throw the sticks up in the air.
那样怎么能算是摇滚乐呢？
What is rock 'n' roll about that?
嘿 乔伊 送你另一个礼物
Hey, Joey, I got you another present.
等一下 先不要告诉我是什么…
Hold it! Before you tell me what it is...
好 是什么？
Okay, what is it?
是一只…
It's a...
毒蜘蛛
...tarantula!
哦
Oh.
天啊 瑞秋 抱歉 我在想什么…
God, Rachel, I'm sorry. What was I thinking...
送乔伊这么一个 恶心的 可怕的蜘蛛…
...giving Joey this big, gross, scary spider...
还用这么一个松散的笼子？
...in such a poorly constructed cage?
你在说什么？我喜欢
What are you talking about? I love them.
我小时候就有一只 后来我的猫咪吃掉了它
I had a tarantula when I was a kid. But it died because my cat ate it.
然后猫咪死了
And then my cat died.
乔伊 这不是很酷吗？
But, Joey, isn't this cool?
在我身上吗？ 我觉得他在我身上 我…
Is it on me? I feel like it's on me. I got...
不是很可爱吗？
Oh, isn't that adorable?
- 乔伊怕蜘蛛   - 哦
- Joey is afraid of the tarantula.     - Oh.
他好可爱哟
He's so adorable.
老天 他很好玩
He's so much fun.
乔伊是最棒的 很高兴你在这里住得很开心
I'm glad you're having so much fun here.
等一下
Whoa. Wait a minute.
菲比 怎么回事？
What's the matter?
我们的房子好了
Our apartment is ready.
你不高兴是因为…？
And that makes you angry because?
因为你比较想和乔伊住在这里
Because you'd rather live here with Joey.
- 你为什么这么想？ - 摩妮卡和钱德…
- Where did you get that?     - Monica and Chandler...
说你和乔伊住得很开心…
...said you were having so much fun here...
而且不管是鼓还是毒蜘殊 都不会改变这点
...and apparently no amount of drums or tarantulas is gonna change that.
菲比 你送乔伊这些东西…
Did you get all this stuff for Joey...
是要让我不想住在这里？
...to try to drive me out of the apartment?
你还不如送他一条鱼
You might as well have gotten him a fish.
你知道我有多怕鱼
You know how fish freak me out.
鱼
Fish.
这些都不重要 我们会一起住的
But it wouldn't have mattered. We're gonna live together.
我们是室友 讲好的
That's the deal.
对 可是我希望你想和我一起住
Yes, but I wanted you to want to live with me.
可是如果你在这里住得这么开心…
But if you're having so much fun over here...
喔 和你在一起更开心
Oh. It's so much more fun with you.
- 我们住一起时很开心 对不对？ - 对啊 好玩的不得了
- We did have fun, didn't we?    - We did.
他们说如果要的话 今晚可以去看
They say if we want, we could see it tonight.
- 好啊   - 好 好
- I would love to.     - Yay, okay!
- 好 好   - 好
- Good, good, good.     - Great. All right. Good.
摩妮卡要我让鼓声停止
And Monica asked me to make the drumming stop.
哦
Um, ahem.
好了
Done.
(万圣节探险 面具大师)
嘿
Hey.
你好 要退还那件裤子吗？
Hello, sir. You here to return those pants?
不 这是我的裤子
No, these are my pants.
喔
Oh.
好吧
Okay.
- 需要什么？ - 还有没有圣诞老公公衣服？
- How can I help you?     - Um, do you have a Santa outfit left?
圣诞节前两天？抱歉
Two days before Christmas? Sorry, man.
好吧 有没有什么 比较算是圣诞节的？
Okay, look. Do you have anything, uh, Christmas-y?
我答应了我儿子 不想让他失望
I promised my son, and I really don't want to disappoint him.
拜托 你们一定有什么吧
Um, come on, you gotta have something.
我是佳节犰狳
I'm the Holiday Armadillo!
我是圣诞老公公的朋友…
I'm a friend of Santa's...
他要我来祝你…
...and he sent me here to wish you...
圣诞快乐
...a merry Christmas!
圣诞老公公怎么了 佳节犰狳？
What happened to Santa, Holiday Armadillo?
圣诞老公公没有空…
Santa was unavailable...
在这么接近圣诞节的时候
...so close to Christmas.
请进 请坐
Come in, have a seat.
你一定累坏了 大老远从德州跑来
You must be exhausted, coming all the way from Texas.
- 德州？ - 对 班
- Texas?     - That's right, Ben.
我是圣诞老公公的…
I'm Santa's representative...
西南州代表
...for all the Southern states.
还有墨西哥
And Mexico!
圣诞老公公要我来这里…
But Santa sent me here...
送礼物给你 班
...to give you these presents, Ben.
或许这位小姐可以帮我拿礼物
Maybe the lady will help me with these presents.
哇 谢谢
Wow, thanks!
不客气 班
You're welcome, Ben.
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas. Ooh.
还有…光明节快乐
And happy Hanukkah!
你也为光明节而来吗？ 因为我是一半犹太人
Are you for Hanukkah too? Because I'm part Jewish.
你是？我也是
You are? Me too.
因为犰狳也在沙漠里游荡？
Because armadillos also wandered in the desert?
你想在走廊游荡吗？
You want to wander in the hall?
班
Oh. Hey, Ben!
何不让佳节犰狳…
What if the Holiday Armadillo...
跟你说光之节的故事好吗？
...told you all about the Festival of Lights?
酷
Cool!
来吧 班
Come on, Ben.
很多年以前…
Years and years ago...
有一群人 叫做…
...there were these people called...
玛加伯人
...the Maccabees!
圣诞快乐
Ho-ho-ho. Merry Christmas!
圣诞老公公
Santa!
嘿
Hey.
你来干什么 圣诞老公公？
What are you doing here, Santa?
我来看我的老朋友班
Well, I'm here to see my old buddy, Ben.
你在这儿干什么…
What are you doing here...
怪…乌龟人？
...Weird Turtle Man?
我是佳节犰狳…
I'm the Holiday Armadillo...
你的半犹太人朋友
...your part-Jewish friend.
你要我来送礼物给班
You sent me here to give Ben some presents.
记得吗？
Remember?
什么？
What?
圣诞老公公 你有带礼物给我吗？
Did you bring me any presents, Santa?
当然有 班
You bet I did, Ben.
放在这里
Put her there.
如果不是他的手太小 这次会成功的
Well, it would have worked this time if his hands weren't so damn small.
呵 呵 呵
Ho-ho-ho.
班 来开礼物
Ben, come open more presents.
圣诞老公公 佳节犰狳和我 要在厨房谈一谈
Santa, the armadillo and I will have a talk in the kitchen.
我绝对想不到会说出这句话
There's a sentence I never thought I'd say.
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
你告诉每个人说 你找不到圣诞老公公衣服…
You said you were having trouble finding a Santa costume...
所以我向同事借了一件
...so I borrowed one from a guy at work.
谢谢 可是你必须离开
Thank you, but you gotta leave.
- 为什么？ - 因为…
- Why?     - Because...
我终于让他对光明节有兴趣…
...I'm finally getting him excited about Hanukkah...
而你正在破坏
...and you're wrecking it.
可是我还没摇我的肚子呢
But I didn't get to shake my belly like a bowlful of jelly.
抱歉 钱德 这对我很重要
I'm sorry, Chandler, but this is really important to me.
好 我去还这套衣服
Fine, I'll give the suit back.
嘿 你可以再多借一晚吗？
Hey, you think you can keep it another night?
圣诞老公公？真的？
Santa, really?
是啊 可以吗？
Yeah, is that okay?
你爸有扮过圣诞老公公吗？
Did your dad ever dress up like Santa?
- 没有   - 那就可以
- No.     - Then it's okay!
班 圣诞老公公要走了
Okay, Ben. Santa has to go.
说再见
Say goodbye.
不要 他为什么要走？
No, why does he have to go?
因为圣诞老公公和佳节…
Because if Santa and the Holiday...
犰狳…
...Armadillo...
如果在同一个房子里太久…
...are ever in the same room for too long...
宇宙会爆炸
...the universe will implode!
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas!
不要 为什么不是犰狳走呢？ 我要圣诞老公公
No, why can't the armadillo leave? I want Santa.
好 我放弃 圣诞老公公…
Fine, I give up. Santa...
圣诞老公公可以留下来
Santa can stay!
我留下来…
Well, I'll stay...
因为我想听光明节的故事
...but only because I want to hear about Hanukkah.
班 你要不要和圣诞老公公…
Ben, will you sit here with Santa...
一起坐下来听光明节的故事？
...and learn about Hanukkah?
好的 圣诞老人
Okay, Santa.
- 谢谢   - 不客气
- Thank you.     - You're welcome.
好 来听…
All right, it's time...
光明节的故事了
...for the story of Hanukkah.
很多年以前…
Years and years ago...
有一群人叫玛加伯人
...there were these people called the Maccabees!
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas!
喔 看看这地方
Oh, wow, look at this place!
真糟糕
Oh, this is terrible.
他们改了很多…
They've made so many changes...
我感受不到我祖母的存在了
...I can't even feel my grandmother's presence anymore.
喔 新的烛台
Oh, new sconces!
- 我的天啊  - 怎么了？
- Oh, my God!     - What?
记得你告诉我你祖母要做一道墙…
Remember, uh, how you told me your grandmother put up that wall...
- 来隔成两间房？ - 对
...to make that into two bedrooms?     - Yeah.
你说房东可能会发现…
And that the landlord might find out...
- 把它拆了？ - 对？
...and then tear it down?     - Yeah?
你真的不知道我说这些的原因？
Do you really not know where I'm going?
墙没有了 是一间大房间
It left. It's one huge room.
哦 不
Oh, no!
哇
Wow!
看吧？
See?
我们必须要把墙弄回来
I guess we'll have to put the wall back up.
- 不行 因为新的天窗   - 有天窗？
- You can't because of the new skylight.     - There's a skylight?
哇
Wow!
我们该怎么办？要开始找新地方吗？
Oh. So should we start looking for a new place?
知道吗？我感受到…
You know, I'm sensing...
我祖母可能不喜欢那样
...that, um, my grandmother would not be comfortable with that.
是吗？
Oh, yeah?
又能感觉到她了 是吗？
Starting to feel her again there, are we?
- 有一点 对   - 是
- A little bit. Yeah.     - Yeah.
菲比 你祖母是不是说 你应该一个人住这里？
Is your grandmother maybe saying that you should live here alone?
你也听见了？你有天分
You heard it too? You have the gift.
菲比 没关系
Phoebe, it's okay.
我喜欢和乔伊住
I like living with Joey.
- 你确定吗？ - 拜托 我讨厌收拾行李…
- Are you sure?     - Please. I hate packing...
那里离公司比较近
...it's closer to work.
我们在一起很开心
And we do have fun.
虽然我真的会想念和你住在一起
Although, I'm really gonna miss living with you.
- 我也是   - 我知道
- Oh, me too.     - I know.
等一下 你有没有听到？
Oh. Did you hear that?
听 我听到你祖母在说话
I'm getting something from your grandmother.
她说既然你要一个人住这里…
She said since you get to keep the one-bedroom apartment...
你该把那把紫色椅子给瑞秋
...you should give Rachel the purple chair.
没有 我没有听到
No, I do not hear that.
奇迹在于那一点点的油…
And the miracle was that that little bit of oil...
应该只够烧一天的 却烧了…
...that should have lasted just one day, burned for...
- 整整8天   - 对
- Eight whole days.     - That's right.
这就是为什么我们 今天庆祝光明节 故事完结
And that's why we celebrate Hanukkah today. The end.
- 好棒   - 是啊
- Awesome.      - Yeah.
我最喜欢的部分…
My favorite part...
是超人救出全埃及的犹太人
...was when Superman flew all the Jews out of Egypt.
犰狳不是那么喜欢那部分
The armadillo was actually not so thrilled about that part.
好 班 该来点…
Okay, Ben, it's time to light...
光明节蜡烛了
...the Hanukkah candles!
哈哈
Ho-ho-ho.
嘿
Hey.
- 哦    - 哇哦
- Oh.     - Wow.
好像是复活节兔子的葬礼
Looks like the Easter Bunny's funeral in here.
来 来 我们要点蜡烛
Come on, come on. We're lighting the candles.
哦 哦
Oh, oh.
我了解为什么超人在这里…
I understand why Superman is here...
但为什么有豪猪 参加复活节兔子的葬礼？
...but why is there a porcupine at the Easter Bunny's funeral?
- 你弄好了吗？ - 弄好了
- You get it?     - I got it.
他进笼子了没？
Back in the cage?
他在笼子里了
It's back in the cage.
笼子关好了吗？
Is the cage closed?
乔伊 出来好吗？ 别像个小孩一样
Joey, will you just come out here and stop being such a baby?